<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-01T09:37:10+00:00</updated><id>https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/feed.xml</id><subtitle>Cosmologist working between theory and experiment with a focus on combined probes and computational methods. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Betelgeuse- A Red Supergiant on the Brink</title><link href="https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/blog/2025/betelgeuse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Betelgeuse- A Red Supergiant on the Brink"/><published>2025-01-31T23:53:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T23:53:16+00:00</updated><id>https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/blog/2025/betelgeuse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/blog/2025/betelgeuse/"><![CDATA[<p>Betelgeuse, one of the brightest stars in the night sky, is a fascinating red supergiant located approximately 550-720 light-years away in the constellation of Orion. As one of Orion’s shoulders, it’s easy to spot - look for the distinctive reddish star in the upper left corner of the famous constellation.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/betelgeuse-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/betelgeuse-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/betelgeuse-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/betelgeuse.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Betelgeuse glowing in its characteristic red hue. Credit: Franco Tognarini/Getty Images/iStock</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>What makes Betelgeuse particularly exciting is its variable brightness, which you can track in real-time through BetelBot on X (formerly Twitter) <a href="https://x.com/betelbot?lang=en&amp;mx=2">here</a> (<em>apologies for the X link!</em>). These dramatic variations in brightness have led to intense speculation about the star’s future - Betelgeuse is near the end of its life and could go supernova at any moment. In fact, given its distance from Earth, it’s possible that Betelgeuse has <em>already</em> exploded, and we’re simply waiting for the light from this cosmic event to reach us!</p> <h2 id="finding-betelgeuse">Finding Betelgeuse</h2> <p>To locate Betelgeuse in the night sky:</p> <ol> <li>Look for Orion’s Belt - three bright stars in a row</li> <li>From the belt, look up and to the left</li> <li>The bright orange-red star you see is Betelgeuse</li> </ol> <p>The best time to observe Betelgeuse is during winter months in the Northern Hemisphere, when Orion is highest in the evening sky.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[betelgeuse facts]]></summary></entry></feed>