<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-01T10:31:15+00:00</updated><id>https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/feed.xml</id><subtitle>Cosmologist working between theory and experiment with a focus on combined probes and computational methods. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Understanding Spin Spherical Harmonics in Cosmology</title><link href="https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/blog/2025/spin_spherical_harmonics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Spin Spherical Harmonics in Cosmology"/><published>2025-02-01T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-01T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/blog/2025/spin_spherical_harmonics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/blog/2025/spin_spherical_harmonics/"><![CDATA[<p>When we look at the sky, we see various cosmic fields painted on the celestial sphere. Some of these fields are simpler than others - they’re just about measuring how bright or hot something is at each point. But others have a more complex geometric nature, involving orientations and patterns that rotate with our viewing perspective. This is where the concept of “spin” comes into play in cosmology.</p> <h2 id="what-makes-a-field-spin">What Makes a Field “Spin”?</h2> <p>Let’s start with some familiar examples:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Spin-0 Fields</strong>: The simplest cosmic fields are scalar fields, which have no preferred direction. The cosmic microwave background (CMB) temperature is a perfect example - at each point on the sky, we just measure a single number representing the temperature. When we rotate our coordinate system, these measurements don’t change. That’s why we call the CMB temperature a spin-0 field.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Spin-2 Fields</strong>: Now consider cosmic shear from weak gravitational lensing. When we observe distant galaxies, their shapes are distorted by the gravitational effects of matter along the line of sight. This distortion has both a magnitude (how much the galaxy is stretched) and a direction (the axis along which the stretching occurs). Here’s the crucial part: if we rotate our coordinate system by an angle ψ, the measured shear components transform with a factor of e^{2iψ}. This factor of 2 in the exponential is why we call it a spin-2 field.</p> </li> </ol> <h2 id="mathematical-description">Mathematical Description</h2> <p>To describe these fields mathematically, we need spin spherical harmonics. Regular (spin-0) spherical harmonics \(Y_{lm}(\theta,\phi)\) are familiar from quantum mechanics, but for spin-s fields, we need their generalization, \(_{s}Y_{lm}(\theta,\phi)\).</p> <p>The spin-weighted spherical harmonics satisfy: \(\eth \,_{s}Y_{lm} = \sqrt{(l-s)(l+s+1)}\,_{s+1}Y_{lm}\) \(\bar{\eth} \,_{s}Y_{lm} = -\sqrt{(l+s)(l-s+1)}\,_{s-1}Y_{lm}\)</p> <p>where \(\eth\) and \(\bar{\eth}\) are the spin-raising and spin-lowering operators respectively. These operators are the spherical analogs of quantum mechanical ladder operators, and they help us understand how to move between different spin states.</p> <h2 id="the-spin-raising-and-lowering-operators">The Spin Raising and Lowering Operators</h2> <p>The explicit form of these operators in spherical coordinates is: \(\eth = -\sin^s\theta\left(\frac{\partial}{\partial\theta} + \frac{i}{\sin\theta}\frac{\partial}{\partial\phi}\right)\sin^{-s}\theta\) \(\bar{\eth} = -\sin^{-s}\theta\left(\frac{\partial}{\partial\theta} - \frac{i}{\sin\theta}\frac{\partial}{\partial\phi}\right)\sin^{s}\theta\)</p> <p>These might look intimidating, but they’re deeply connected to something familiar from quantum mechanics: angular momentum operators.</p> <h2 id="connection-to-quantum-mechanics">Connection to Quantum Mechanics</h2> <p>The similarity to quantum mechanics isn’t coincidental. Just as the angular momentum raising and lowering operators \(L_±\) help us navigate between different angular momentum states, \(\eth\) and \(\bar{\eth}\) help us move between different spin states. In fact, we can write:</p> \[L_± = L_x \pm iL_y\] <p>which is analogous to how we construct spin operators from the directional derivatives on the sphere.</p> <h2 id="application-to-cosmic-shear">Application to Cosmic Shear</h2> <p>For weak lensing, we typically work with spin-2 fields. The shear field \(\gamma(\theta,\phi)\) can be decomposed into E-modes and B-modes:</p> \[\gamma(\theta,\phi) = \sum_{lm} (E_{lm} + iB_{lm})\, _{2}Y_{lm}(\theta,\phi)\] <p>This decomposition is crucial because:</p> <ol> <li>E-modes are created by gravitational lensing (to first order)</li> <li>B-modes should be zero in the absence of systematics</li> <li>This provides a powerful way to check for systematic errors in our measurements</li> </ol> <h2 id="visualizing-spin-fields">Visualizing Spin Fields</h2> <p>To understand spin fields visually:</p> <ul> <li>Spin-0: Think of a temperature map, where each point just has a value</li> <li>Spin-1: Think of a vector field, like wind directions on a weather map</li> <li>Spin-2: Think of headless vectors or ellipses, like the shapes of galaxies in a weak lensing map</li> </ul> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>&lt;!--
  See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
  https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
--&gt;

  &lt;source
    class="responsive-img-srcset"
    srcset="/assets/img/spin_fields-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/spin_fields-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/spin_fields-1400.webp 1400w,"
    
      sizes="95vw"
    
    type="image/webp"
  &gt;

&lt;img
  src="/assets/img/spin_fields.jpg"
  
    class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1"
  
  
    width="100%"
  
  
    height="auto"
  
  
  
  
  
    data-zoomable
  
  
    loading="lazy"
  
  onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"
&gt;
</code></pre></div></div> <p>&lt;/picture&gt;</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>&lt;figcaption class="caption"&gt;Visualization of different spin fields on the sphere. Left: Spin-0 (temperature). Center: Spin-1 (vectors). Right: Spin-2 (ellipses).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
</code></pre></div></div> <p>&lt;/figure&gt;</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div></div> <p>&lt;/div&gt; –&gt;</p> <h2 id="practical-implementation">Practical Implementation</h2> <p>In practice, computing spin spherical harmonics involves:</p> <ol> <li>Starting with regular spherical harmonics</li> <li>Applying spin raising/lowering operators numerically</li> <li>Using recursion relations for efficiency</li> </ol> <p>Popular codes like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">healpy</code> implement these calculations efficiently, allowing us to work with full-sky maps of spin-2 fields.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>Spin spherical harmonics provide the mathematical framework needed to properly analyze geometric fields on the sky. While the mathematics can seem daunting, the underlying concepts connect beautifully to quantum mechanics and provide powerful tools for modern cosmological analysis.</p> <p>In future posts, we’ll explore how these concepts apply to specific analyses in weak lensing and what we can learn about the universe from these measurements.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="math"/><category term="cosmology"/><category term="weak-lensing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A deep dive into the mathematics of spin spherical harmonics and their applications in cosmology]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Betelgeuse- A Red Supergiant on the Brink</title><link href="https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/blog/2025/betelgeuse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Betelgeuse- A Red Supergiant on the Brink"/><published>2025-01-31T23:53:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T23:53:16+00:00</updated><id>https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/blog/2025/betelgeuse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https:/alexander-reeves.github.io/blog/2025/betelgeuse/"><![CDATA[<p>Betelgeuse, one of the brightest stars in the night sky, is a fascinating red supergiant located approximately 550-720 light-years away in the constellation of Orion. As one of Orion’s shoulders, it’s easy to spot - look for the distinctive reddish star in the upper left corner of the famous constellation.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/betelgeuse-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/betelgeuse-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/betelgeuse-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/betelgeuse.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Betelgeuse glowing in its characteristic red hue. Credit: Franco Tognarini/Getty Images/iStock</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>What makes Betelgeuse particularly exciting is its variable brightness, which you can track in real-time through BetelBot on X (formerly Twitter) <a href="https://x.com/betelbot?lang=en&amp;mx=2">here</a> (<em>apologies for the X link!</em>). These dramatic variations in brightness have led to intense speculation about the star’s future - Betelgeuse is near the end of its life and could go supernova at any moment. In fact, given its distance from Earth, it’s possible that Betelgeuse has <em>already</em> exploded, and we’re simply waiting for the light from this cosmic event to reach us!</p> <h2 id="finding-betelgeuse">Finding Betelgeuse</h2> <p>To locate Betelgeuse in the night sky:</p> <ol> <li>Look for Orion’s Belt - three bright stars in a row</li> <li>From the belt, look up and to the left</li> <li>The bright orange-red star you see is Betelgeuse</li> </ol> <p>The best time to observe Betelgeuse is during winter months in the Northern Hemisphere, when Orion is highest in the evening sky.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[betelgeuse facts]]></summary></entry></feed>